Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's daf דף daf is
hey ה hey and we're continuing in the Gemara גמרא Gemara in
its discussion of the idea that Nissan ניסן Nissan is Rosh Hashanah
l'regalim ראש השנה לרגלים, Rosh Hashanah l'regalim, which means that it starts
the cycle for the count for the moadim
מועדים moadim for the issue of bal t'acher בל תאחר bal t'acher
of not postponing bringing your obligatory sacrifice or the vows and other
types of obligations as what something we'll unpack in a minute today
and then we saw in the Gemara גמרא Gemara yesterday a Baraita
ברייתא Baraita that discussed different opinions about when you transgress bal t'acher
בל תאחר. bal t'acher. The first three, the three going in order
starting from Pesach פסח Pesach which is the assumption of our Mishnah
משנה Mishnah which makes Nissan ניסן Nissan the Rosh Hashanah ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah the beginning of the cycle, or once you hit Sukkot
סוכות Sukkot regardless of how many chagim חגים chagim or any two
or any one, a whole range of different opinions. Okay, and now
the Gemara גמרא Gemara is finishing to work through
the
various pesukim פסוקים pesukim that are used to prove or as the
basis for the various positions. Yes.
I have a question about the need to remain overnight in Yerushalayim
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Yes.
T'chum תחום T'chum applies on Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov as
well. Right. So that was an instituted requirement on its own without
having to have a special rule.
Well, the need to overnight is not overnight after the chag hapesach
חג הפסח, chag hapesach, it's after the morning sacrifices of the olat
re'iah עולת ראיה olat re'iah and the shalmei chagigah שלמי חגיגה, shalmei
chagigah, the olat re'iah עולת ראיה olat re'iah primarily and also the
shalmei chagigah שלמי חגיגה. shalmei chagigah. Right, so on the second night.
Yes, exactly. And that if you take a look at Rashi רש"י
Rashi and that was one of the things we ended with yesterday,
the first Rashi רש"י Rashi ufarnisa vaboker ופנית בבוקר ufarnisa vaboker on
this daf דף daf says beyom tov lo amar kra ביום טוב
לא אמר קרא beyom tov lo amar kra sheharei hu yom shechiyuvo
lera'ot ba'azarah שהרי הוא יום שחיובו לראות בעזרה. sheharei hu yom shechiyuvo
lera'ot ba'azarah. It's not saying you go home in the morning of
Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov because that's the day you have
to appear in the Azarah עזרה. Azarah. So you're going home the
morning following Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov after you've brought your
olat re'iah עולת ראיה. olat re'iah. So that was anyway one of
the things that the Gemara גמרא Gemara said about what you do
from some of the verses that the connecting of the pesukim פסוקים
pesukim of Chag Hamatzot חג המצות Chag Hamatzot and Chag Hasukkot חג
הסוכות Chag Hasukkot is to tell you that the same way there's
an obligation in Sukkot סוכות Sukkot to in Pesach פסח Pesach with,
let's read it again, Mah Chag Hamatzot taun linah af Chag Hasukkot
taun linah מה חג המצות טעון לינה אף חג הסוכות טעון לינה.
Mah Chag Hamatzot taun linah af Chag Hasukkot taun linah. And again,
looking at various pesukim פסוקים pesukim of the moadim מועדים moadim whether
it's to tell you how many chagim חגים chagim is needed for
bal t'acher בל תאחר bal t'acher or whether it's telling you something
else and here according to one opinion what it's telling you is
this issue of that there's an idea of staying over the next
night. And Tosafot תוספות Tosafot is trying to decide isn't there generally
an obligation to stay over the night after bringing korbanot קרבנות, korbanot,
but okay that's what the Gemara גמרא Gemara says. Vehasam minalan והתם
מנלן Vehasam minalan how do you know by Pesach פסח Pesach you
have to stay over the first night, not of the Korban Pesach
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach but the first night of after the first
day after appearing as Rashi רש"י Rashi just said in the Azarah
עזרה? Azarah? Dechtiv דכתיב Dechtiv the verse says ufarnita vaboker vehalachta liohalecha
ופנית בבוקר והלכת לאהליך. ufarnita vaboker vehalachta liohalecha. You'll turn in the
morning and you'll go back to your tent and therefore and so
therefore you presumably meaning only wait till the morning and similarly on
Sukkot סוכות Sukkot as well, after you do only leave not as
soon as it's Motzei Yom Tov Rishon מוצאי יום טוב ראשון Motzei
Yom Tov Rishon but you can only leave the next morning. It
is interesting by the way that this only appears by Pesach פסח
Pesach and not by Sukkot סוכות Sukkot and part of the reason
is is by Sukkot סוכות Sukkot the Torah תורה Torah assumes that
you're spending the whole week in Yerushalayim ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It says right
v'samachta lifnei Hashem Elokecha shivat yamim ושמחת לפני ה' אלהיך שבעת ימים
v'samachta lifnei Hashem Elokecha shivat yamim and so on. V'hayita ach sameach
והיית אך שמח. V'hayita ach sameach. Sukkot סוכות Sukkot is the end
of the cycle, you've harvested everything in, you can take a little
bit of a vacation, you can spend a little bit of time
enjoying all of the harvest, all of the good. Pesach פסח Pesach
is right in the middle of the working year. Pesach פסח Pesach
you have to go back and you have to finish the harvest,
you only began cutting down the wheat and so on. So Pesach
פסח Pesach you're more heading back more quickly to your tent, going
back home and that's this pasuk פסוק pasuk about but still you
wait till the next morning.
So they're going home the first day of Chol Hamoed חול המועד.
Chol Hamoed. First day of Chol Hamoed חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. Okay.
So now Gemara גמרא Gemara says ve-Tanna Kamma ve-Rabbi Shimon tashlumin l'Atzeret
minalhu ותנא קמא ורבי שמעון תשלומין לעצרת מנלהו. ve-Tanna Kamma ve-Rabbi Shimon
tashlumin l'Atzeret minalhu. So the Tanna Kamma תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and
Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who were the ones that held
that bal t'acher בל תאחר bal t'acher is only it's three regalim
רגלים regalim or bal t'acher בל תאחר bal t'acher is any three
or either three in the right order. So therefore what do they
do because in terms of this idea of tashlumin תשלומין tashlumin that
you have the other seven days on of Shavuot שבועות Shavuot to
satisfy your obligations of the shalmei chagigah שלמי חגיגה shalmei chagigah and
so on. Before we learned this from the fact that those were
considered to be extra, didn't have to say Chag Hamatzot veChag Hashavuot
veChag Hasukkot חג המצות וחג השבועות וחג הסוכות. Chag Hamatzot veChag Hashavuot
veChag Hasukkot. But according to Tanna Kamma תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and
Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon they learn from the fact that
the Torah תורה Torah repeats all the chagim חגים chagim to tell
you that you need three chagim חגים chagim for bal t'acher בל
תאחר. bal t'acher. So if that's what the Torah תורה Torah is
telling you by repeating those, why how do you learn this idea
that there's this idea of tashlumin תשלומין tashlumin on Shavuot שבועות Shavuot
that if you don't bring the requisite korbanot קרבנות korbanot on the
first day you have actually the whole week? You can't say because
it's linked to Pesach פסח Pesach because it's not repeated for the
sake of being linked, it's repeated for the sake of telling you
that you need the three regalim רגלים regalim in order to be
bal t'acher בל תאחר. bal t'acher. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says
no, nafka lehu midetani Rabba bar Shmuel נפקא להו מדתני רבא בר
שמואל. nafka lehu midetani Rabba bar Shmuel. They learn it from... They
learn it out from where רבא בר שמואל *Rabba bar Shmuel* teaches.
דתניא detanya, *detania*, we taught in a ברייתא braita, *braita*, רבא בר
שמואל אמר תורה Torah *Rabba bar Shmuel amar Torah*, the תורה Torah
*Torah* says מני ימים וקדש חודש *manei yamim ve-kadesh chodesh*, count days
and sanctify the new month. The new month, so the ראש חודש
*Rosh Chodesh* is after a certain amount of days. Now it's not
really after a certain amount of days because the days vary, it's
after you know it's after the new moon is seen, but nevertheless
the concept is that the month is made up of days. And
therefore ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*, the holiday of ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*
lasts for, I mean the holiday,
but the day of ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* is in terms of
its significance in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit Hamikdash* is one
day. So therefore in parallel מני ימים וקדש עצרת *manei yamim ve-kadesh
Atzeret*. So count days and make a שבועות Shavuot, *Shavuot*. Now מה
חודש למנייו *mah chodesh limnuyav*, the same way a ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh* is based on its the number of the things you count
to get to it, so 29 or 30 days, but it's made
up of days and therefore the ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* itself is
one day. אף af עצרת למנייו *af Atzeret limnuyav*. So שבועות Shavuot,
*Shavuot* goes by the units you count to get to שבועות *Shavuot*.
Now what units do you count to get to שבועות *Shavuot*? You
count days but you also count weeks, you know more primarily the
תורה *Torah* emphasizes שבע שבתות תמימות תהיינה *sheva shabbatot temimot tihyena*. So
therefore there's a concept of a week of שבועות *Shavuot* and therefore
that week the significance is not that it's a יום טוב *Yom
Tov* for the whole week but that significance is for the bringing
of קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי
עצרת חד יומא *ei Atzeret chad yoma*, one minute but no but
you know maybe עצרת *Atzeret* should be one day because it's also
made up of 50 days or 49 days not just seven weeks.
סו אמר רבא אטו עצרת יומי מנינן שבועי לא מנינן *So amar
Rava atu Atzeret yomei maninan shavu'ei lo maninan*? Why do you mean
to tell me that you only count days when you do ספירת
העומר *Sefirat HaOmer* you don't count weeks? והאמר מר *Ve-ha-amar Mar*, so
very appropriate see it's during ספירת העומר *Sefirat HaOmer* מצוה mitzvah למני
יומי ומצוה למני שבועי *mitzvah le-menei yomei u-mitzvah le-menei shavu'ei*, there's a
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to count the days and a מצוה *mitzvah* to
count the weeks and that's how we do our ספירה *sefira*. Interestingly
by the way some say that the actual מצוה *mitzvah* of the
weeks is only on the whole weeks which is actually today so
you could say 28 days which is four weeks but like for
the next six days you would just say it's 29 days it's
30 days it's 31 days and then only when you got to
35 you'd say it's 35 days which is five weeks which makes
a certain amount of sense because you're counting units of weeks not
like partial weeks. But anyway so this actually I gotta tell you
quite fascinating normally you know this idea okay you have a week
to make it up for שבועות *Shavuot* תשלומין *tashlumin* we don't give
any significance we figure out some הלכה halacha, *halakha* by קרבנות korbanot
*korbanot*, you know you learn it out from you know you learn
it out from the other חגים chagim. *chagim*. It also has נפקא
מינה *nafka mina* for issues of אבילות *avelut* by the way but
okay but anyway the but what's fascinating here is the sense that
actually maybe has to do with the identity, you know שבועות *Shavuot*
is 50 is after is 49 days and is seven weeks and
maybe there's an idea to which it's a חג *chag* that is
both a one day חג *chag* and a one week חג *chag*.
The one week חג *chag* only is expressed in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash* in the context of קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot* but
it's an interesting way of thinking about שבועות *Shavuot*. Yes.
A couple of short questions. First of all here it says אמרה
תורה *amra Torah*, it's not a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. That's right it's
not it's sort of a funny
yeah I mean it's the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks it's
about how we're interpreting you know the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* of the
תורה *Torah* and what our biblical mandates are but yes correct.
Most Jews never even made it to ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* once in
their life for a רגל regel? *Regel*. Okay. So if you've all
those people were עובר over בל תאחר bal te'acher *over bal tacher*
or it's only if you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* but you're not
משלים *mashlim* the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*?
No it's it's no even if you never make it to ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* but
first of all if you're not making it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* you
shouldn't be taking a נדר Neder *neder* to bring
קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. Okay. So right.
Do you have to take a נדר Neder. *neder* to bring עולת
ראיה olat re'iyah *olat re'iyah*?
No so that's true meaning there are certain things here like the
עולת ראיה olat re'iyah? *olat re'iyah* and the שלמי חגיגה shalmei chagigah
*shalmei chagiga* and the you know if you're חייב *chayav* a חטאת
Chatat *chatat* and so on. Okay so those are obligations. I mean
you know you could always have somebody bring like some of the
stuff other than the עולת ראיה olat re'iyah *olat re'iyah* which is
about you know of you but you know you could always have
somebody bring קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* for you and send it with somebody
that is going to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. But yes it is interesting we'll
get to that in a minute that you know the פסוקים pesukim
*pesukim* are focused completely on satisfying your vows and the way the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* broadens it it's not limited to vows it has
to do with just obligations and it's an interesting weird collection of
obligations. So but it is not about having been in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*
and having had the opportunity no it's you know it's an obligation
to bring regardless and so therefore to make your way to ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* or get it sent to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*.
And also when you said there's a נפקא מינה *nafka mina* for
אבילות *avelut* I thought you were going to say a נפקא מינה
*nafka mina* for תפילה tefillah *tefillah* let's say I don't דאוון *daven*
like on יום טוב *Yom Tov* I don't have a week to
make
that up.
No no no
no no yeah yeah yeah yeah right exactly.
Okay so
let's take a look. גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this ועוד חג
שבועות
*Ve-od Chag Shavuot*
okay I'm sorry ועוד *Ve-od*. ועוד חג שבועות כתיב
*V'od Chag Shavuos ksiv*. All right, that's the simple point. It says
the חג *Chag* of weeks, so there's a concept of the week
of the חג *Chag* having some status of a week. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, so now we're done about the פסוקים
*psukim*. Now we get to unpack the rest of the ברייתא braita.
*Baraisa* which speaks about the things that you are over on בל
תאחר bal te'acher *bal t'acher* for. Okay, so if you look by
the way back at the ברייתא braita *Baraisa*, the ברייתא braita *Baraisa*
listed it, right, it said,
right, if you battle of בל תאחר bal te'acher? *bal t'acher*, חייבי
דמים damim, וערכין וחרמים והקדשות חטאות ואשמות עולות ושלמים Chataot veAshamot Olot
uShlamim, צדקות tzedakos ומעשרות umasrot, בכור bechor. ומעשר ופסח *chayvei damim v'erchin
v'charamin v'hekdeshos chatos v'ashamos olos u'shelamim tzedakos u'maasros bechor u'maaser v'pesach*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to jump to פסח Pesach. *Pesach*,
although there's a lot to say about the list that preceded פסח
Pesach? *Pesach*. We'll go back to that, but first the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* wants to say how you are over on בל תאחר bal
te'acher? *bal t'acher* by פסח Pesach *Pesach*. Let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says by not having brought it on the
other רגלים regalim *regalim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ופסח בר
מקרא ברגלים הוא *U'pesach bar mikra b'regalim hu*?
Can you bring the פסח Pesach. *Pesach* on the other רגלים regalim?
*regalim* that you could be over on בל תאחר bal te'acher *bal
t'acher* if you didn't bring it on פסח Pesach, *Pesach*? Because you
then didn't bring it on שבועות *Shavuos* and then סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkos*?
I mean on שבועות *Shavuos* and then סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkos*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פסח Pesach, זימנא קביעה ליה *Pesach zimna kvia
lei*. So the פסח Pesach. *Pesach* has a fixed time. אי אקריביה
אקריביה *Ei akrivye akrivye*, if you brought it on the fourteenth of
ניסן *Nissan*, you brought it, ואי לא אקריביה אידחיה ליה *v'ei lo
akrivye idchaya lei*, and if you didn't bring it, it gets pushed
off and you know, you don't bring it anymore. So אמר רב
חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*, פסח Pesach כדי נסבה *Pesach k'dei nasba*. Fine,
פסח Pesach *Pesach* was just quoted for nothing, meaning
we're
giving a long list
so it's sort of it gets כדי *k'dei* means for naught, means
you know, it was sort of like
it's what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* elsewhere calls like שיגרא דלישנא *shigra
d'lishna*, you know, you're just doing a long list of all your
obligations. You got it, this, this, this and פסח Pesach. *Pesach* and
this, all right, I didn't think about פסח pesach *Pesach*. פסח pesach
*Pesach* actually you can't is not relevant, fine, take off פסח pesach
*Pesach*. So you know, but it's basically saying it's not taught to
teach you anything, it's taught because it was part of a long
list of things, so it got quoted in the list of קרבנות
korbanot *korbanos*, but it really doesn't belong there. רב ששת אמר *Rav
Sheshes amar*, רב ששת *Rav Sheshes* says, מאי פסח *Mai Pesach*? No,
what does פסח *Pesach* mean? שלמי פסח *Shalmei Pesach*. It means a
שלמים Shelamim *shelamim* that a פסח *Pesach* that converted into a שלמים
shlamim, *shelamim*. If you do not bring your קרבן korban פסח *korban
Pesach*, you sanctified your animal and then let's say it got lost
and you had to bring another one for קרבן korban פסח *korban
Pesach*, and then you found it, that thing that was a קרבן
korban. פסח *korban Pesach* now has a status of a שלמים shlamim
*shelamim*. So that thing has three רגלים regalim. *regalim* to be brought.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי היינו שלמים shelamim *Ei
hachi hainu shelamim*? So why do you have to tell it to
me, you already told me your שלמים shelamim. *shelamim*, what do I
care what type of a שלמים *shelamim* it is? It's a שלמים
*shelamim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, חד שלמים הבאים מחמת
הפסח וחד שלמים הבאים מחמת עצמן *Chad shelamim habaim machmas haPesach v'chad
shelamim habaim machmas atzman*. It tells you a שלמים *shelamim* that had
come from a פסח *Pesach* that had been a פסח *Pesach* that
had transitioned that had converted, and it tells you a normal שלמים
*shelamim*. סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach amina, *Salka daitach amina*, I would
have thought, הואיל ומחמת פסח קאתו *Hoil u'machmas Pesach ka'asu*, since it
originated from the פסח *Pesach*, כפסח דמי *k'Pesach dami*, it's like a
פסח *Pesach*. And what does that mean? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
וברגל ראשון יעבור עליה *U'veregal rishon yaavor aleha*, maybe the same way
you didn't satisfy your obligation if you didn't bring your פסח *Pesach*
on the first day, on the fourteenth of ניסן *Nissan*, maybe this
would be like a quasi-פסח *quasi-Pesach* and at your first opportunity you
will transgress. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan *Ka mashma lan* that
no, that you need the normal three רגלים regalim, *regalim*. It's a
little different because by פסח *Pesach* you don't transgress a לאו דלא
תאחר לשלמו leshalmo, *lav d'lo s'acher l'shalmo*, you transgress an עשה *asei*,
it's a very weighty עשה *asei*. Also by פסח *Pesach* you transgress
it by not bringing it on the fourteenth, here you would transgress
it by not bringing it on the first רגל regel. *regel*. But
meaning the same way פסח *Pesach* has one time to be brought,
maybe this would have one time to be brought and not three
opportunities? No, once it's a שלמים *shelamim* it has the normal rules
of a שלמים *shelamim*.
Why isn't פסח שני *Pesach Sheini* thinking about tomorrow? Why isn't פסח
שני *Pesach Sheini* relevant here?
פסח שני *Pesach Sheini* is relevant in terms of your personal obligation,
but not in terms of the status of the קרבן korban, *korban*.
What what relevance would you want it to have?
Well, if you didn't bring, you didn't bring the קרבן korban. *korban*,
why couldn't you bring it a month later?
This this thing that became a שלמים *shelamim*, why can't it be
brought at פסח שני *Pesach Sheini*? So it could, but when it's
not the but in the period where it's not first of all,
that's why רש"י Rashi *Rashi* gives the scenario about נתכפרו באחר nitkapru
be-acher? *niscapru b'acher*, you used another קרבן korban, *korban*, you were יוצא
yotze, *yotzei*. So therefore it's not going to be a פסח שני
*Pesach Sheini*, you personally גברא *gavra* we would say were יוצא yotzei
*yotzei*. It's just that this animal wasn't brought, so the animal became
a שלמים *shelamim*. What actually is the story about a פסח *Pesach*
that you missed the opportunity that you didn't bring it and would
it automatically become a קרבן korban, *korban*? Yeah, a שלמים *shelamim* or
retain a status of a קרבן korban *korban*? Yeah, someone remember the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in פסחים *Pesachim*, I don't remember the specifics of
that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, now,
מנה הני מילי *M'na hanei mili*? Now we're going to try to
look at all that whole long list of things and I should
say that there's some logical problems with the list of things you're
over on בל תאחר bal te'acher. *bal t'acher*. If you go through
the list, okay, חייבי דמים וערכין וחרמים והקדשות *chayvei damim v'erchin v'charamin
v'hekdeshos*.
So חייבי דמים וערכין *chayvei damim v'erchin* is you take an obligation
to give money to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay,
now that's you know fits in the
פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, right? כי תידור נדר neder. לה' l'Hashem? *Ki sidor
neder l'Hashem*... So you make a vow, you make a vow to
give money, you don't be late in paying it up, fine. But
חרמים והקדשות, or let's even talk about הקדשות, Hekdeshot, wants to point
out that you could say well isn't that similar to giving something
to God? But you know, if I sanctify my car to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you have to think in the case and
who owns my car right now? I sanctify my car, המקדשתי את
המכונית. hikdashti et hamchonit. Who owns it? The בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
owns it. If I sanctify my animal as an עולה, olah, it's
not fully, it's קדוש kadosh as an עולה, olah, but it's not
like it's the property of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash That's more
about the way in which it's going to be used as opposed
to an issue of ownership. But when I sanctify my car to
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that transfers the ownership. It's about the
בית המקדש Beis haMikdash. now owns it. So if you think about
it, מי אמירתו לגבוה כמיסירתו להדיוט.
mi amirato legavoah
kemsirato lehedyot.
Well, yes, number one, yeah exactly, like your car, you call up
whatever, you know, the donate your car and one of the good
things is that they come and they take care of it for
you. But besides that, you know, there's a picking it up. They
already own it when you give it to them, you're not transferring
its ownership, you're just delivering something that they now own.
So to say you're מקידשו, makdisho, yes,
אמירתו לגבוה כמיסירתו להדיוט, amirato legavoah kemsirato lehedyot, right, your words of
מקידש makdish is like you've handed it over. So it is a
little bit ironic that you would be over on בל תאחר bal
te'acher because they actually do own it. Your delay is only delay
in delivering to them something that they actually already own. Okay, but
you know, so that's that בל תאחר bal te'acher is a surprise.
That's number one. Then חטאות ואשמות עולות ושלמים, Olot uShlamim so עולות
ושלמים Olot uShlamim. could just mean a normal עולות ושלמים. We'll see
in the גמרא Gemara what it means. But a חטאת Chatat and
an אשם Asham is something you're obligated in. Right? So if I
go ahead and I sin, right, and I'm חייב חטאת, chayav Chatat,
I sin בשוגג, beshogeg, so now even if I've never taken said
I'm מקידש makdish this animal for חטאת Chatat or whatever, the clock
starts running and after שלוש רגלים, shalosh regalim, I'm over. Well, that's
not כי תדור נדר לה' אלוהיך לא תאחר לשלמו. Ki tidor neder
l'Hashem Elokecha lo te'acher leshalmo. I'm being מאחר me'acher to be to
fulfill my obligations in terms of קרבנות, korbanot but I'm not being
מאחר me'acher in fulfilling my vows. I didn't vow anything. Okay? So
that's number one, that's a little bit strange. Okay. Now also the
other thing which we'll see in the גמרא Gemara is let's say
I actually take a free will obligation, but I don't say הרי
עלי, harei alai, I am going to accept an obligation to bring
an עולה. olah. I take this nice cow and say הרי זו
עולה. harei zo olah. I sanctify this as an עולה. olah. So
is that a לא תאחר לשלמו? lo te'acher leshalmo? Meaning, my vow,
my vow wasn't to do something, my words sanctified the object. So
now I'm not delaying fulfilling my word, the effect of my words.
In a way there, there is a delay because the point of
sanctifying the object was to bring it, but again, that's not the
sense of I've obligated myself and I haven't satisfied my obligation, my
obligation, my vow. Okay? So there's a couple of חידושים chidushim there
that, okay, but there at least maybe it's the easiest one you
could say that once it becomes a קרבן korban and the point
of a קרבן korban is to bring it, it's like I haven't
satisfied the purpose of that vow until I've delivered it and brought
it as a קרבן. korban But I think it's a bigger חידוש
chidush to say that's one thing when it's about bringing a קרבן,
korban it's another thing when I sanctify my car and it's about
הקדש Hekdesh just come and pick it up. And it's yet another
thing when it's not even an obligation, when it's not even about
a vow, it's about a חטאת chatat and an אשם, Asham, just
an obligation. And then you get to these other things,
צדקה מעשרות בכור לקט שכחה ופאה Tzedakah, Ma'asrot, Bechor, Leket, Shikcha uPe'ah
which A, aren't to the בית המקדש and B, some of them
aren't a vow like לקט שכחה ופאה, Leket, Shikcha uPe'ah, right? And
another priority, it's just I haven't given my לקט שכחה ופאה, Leket,
Shikcha uPe'ah, right? לקט שכחה ופאה Leket, Shikcha uPe'ah is stuff you
drop. So צדקה Tzedakah at least you could say comes from a
vow, right? I make a commitment, a vow to give צדקה. Tzedakah.
But how about מעשר? Ma'aser? How about... and now מעשר Ma'aser you
could say you separate מעשר Ma'aser with your word, your word sanctified
this מעשר. Ma'aser. But לקט שכחה ופאה, Leket, Shikcha uPe'ah, that's stuff
that I dropped and that I leave to the עניים. aniyim. It's
not to the בית המקדש, it's not through a vow.
To what degree, well and you don't even give it, you leave
it behind which we'll talk about. But even if there was something
about giving it, so where does that fit into בל תאחר? bal
te'acher You know, so what, any religious obligation I don't satisfy is
all of a sudden בל תאחר? bal te'acher. So it's a very
strange list. So let's take a look or it's a surprising list,
I should say. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara now.
Back to דף ה עמוד ב.
daf
he amud bet.
Except for... oh it does... he fly it... it flies it to
the contribution of the צדקה Tzedakah exactly.
But at least צדקה Tzedakah makes sense, there's a vow aspect to
צדקה. Tzedakah. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מנלן הני
מילי? menalan hani milei? Where does all this come from? Top of
דף ה עמוד ב. daf he amud bet.
דתנו רבנן detanu rabanan our rabbis taught, כי תדור נדר Ki tidor
neder when you make a vow, אין לי אלא נדר ein li
ela neder I only know a vow which you say I accept
upon myself to bring a קרבן. korban. נדבה מנין nedavah minayin if
you sanctify the animal directly, how do you know that it's a
בל תאחר bal te'acher issue?
כנאמר כאן נדר ונאמר להלן או נדר או נדבה זבח קרבנו. kene'emar
kan neder vene'emar lehalan o neder o nedavah zevach korbano. Okay,
fine.
מה להלן נדבה עמו, Ma lehalan nidavah imo, the same way there
נדר neder includes the idea of a נדבה, Nidavah, אף כאן נדבה
עמו, Af kan nidavah imo, here too as well. So the חידוש
chidush number one as I've already said is when you say הרי
זו עולה, Harei zu olah, your vow is immediately fulfilled, the animal
is sanctified. So you could say what do you mean I'm not
being מאחר לשלם, meacher leshalem, I sanctified the animal and that's it.
Okay, but there, as there, it's not a huge חידוש chidush because
the idea of saying הרי זו עולה Harei zu olah is in
order that it be brought. So the ultimate fulfillment of the vow,
that it be brought, has not yet, you know, has not yet
reached its climax, reached its actual fulfillment. That's חידוש chidush number one.
Okay, so that's כי תדור נדר Ki tidor neder לה' אלהיך, laShem
Elokecha, to Hashem your God, אלו הדמים הערכין החרמין וההקדשות. Elu ha'damim
ha'erachin hacharamim vehakdeshot. These are things that are sanctified to the temple
treasury, ערך erech and דמים, you say I accept upon myself to
pay myself the value of something, or ערך erech which is the
fixed value in the Torah, חרמין והקדשות charamim ve'hekdeshot is you sanctify
the object. So again, this is including the idea of that's- רש"י
Rashi says the reason we learn it out from לה' אלהיך laShem
Elokecha as opposed to קרבנות where the כהנים Kohanim get a part
of the קרבן, korban even in an עולה Olah they get the
leather and the skin, this is all to God. And that's learned
from the aspect לה' אלהיך. laShem Elokecha. But again, the חידוש chidush
of הקדשות hekdeshot is significant because when you sanctify your car, it
now belongs to the בית המקדש. The only thing left to do
is to deliver it. But the actual ownership and transfer has occurred
and nevertheless that's included in בל תאחר. bal tascher. לא תאחר לשלמו,
Lo te'acher leshalmo, you should not postpone paying it up, satisfy-
הוא ולא חילופו, hu velo chilufo, it לשלמו, leshalmo, but not its
substitute. You don't transgress בל תאחר bal tascher. by its substitute. We'll
see what that means in the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara will
unpack that. כי דרוש ידרשנו ה' אלהיך מעמך, Ki darosh yidrashenu Hashem
Elokecha me'imach, God will seek it out from you, payment, if you
have not done it. אלו חטאות ואשמות עולות ושלמים. Elu chata'ot va'ashamot
olot ushlamim. This is a חטאת chatat, and an אשם, asham, things
that are not coming by a vow but are coming by כי
דרוש ידרשנו, ki darosh yidrashenu, by a demand that God makes. So
even if it's an obligation and not based on a vow. Now
an עולה Olah and a שלמים is generally not an obligation, that's
normally under נדר. neder, But רש"י Rashi. says by עולה ושלמים Olah
ushlamim we're talking about עולת ראיה ושלמי חגיגה. olat re'iyah veshalmei chagigah.
Okay, now which is interesting also, right? Because if you don't bring
your עולת ראיה olat re'iyah on time, right, so you bring it
what? You bring it like next רגל? regel So are you יוצא,
yotzei you know, so I wasn't יוצא עולת ראיה, yotze olat re'iyah,
it's too late to do the מצוה of יראה כל זכורך yera'eh
kol zechurcha because I wasn't עולה oleh for פסח. But if I
go up for שבועות, right, then I bring two עולת ראיה? olat
re'iyah So I'm not over on, you know, so I'm not over
on the בל תאחר bal tascher? from the עולת ראיה olat re'iyah
that I did not bring on פסח? That's a bit of a
strange idea. I think our normal intuition would be that your עולת
ראיה olat re'iyah is, you know, the part of the act of
being there on פסח is bringing the עולה. olah. If you weren't
there, it's over and done with. Okay, so this idea here that
there's a type of a בל תאחר bal tascher? by עולת ראיה
olat re'iyah,
is quite interesting. But that's what רש"י Rashi reads in here because
otherwise he says it's just a- it's
just a normal obligation, it's a normal נדר ונדבה. neder unedavah. Okay,
but if you take a look תוספות Tosafot raises the issue, right?
So תוספות Tosafot says אלו חטאות ואשמות, Elu chata'ot va'ashamot, so תוספות
Tosafot says here, we'll just read it from the beginning,
כי דרוש ידרשנו ממך, Ki darosh yidrashenu mimcha, שהרי הם מוטלים חובה
עליך. sheharei hen mutalin chova alecha. ועולות ושלמים כגון עולת ראיה ושלמי
חגיגה שהם חובה, Ve'olot ushlamim kegon olat re'iyah veshalmei chagigah shehen chova,
שאם לא זבח במועד מחשבה נדר נעשה. she'im lo zivach bamoed machashivah
neder na'aseh. That's quoting רש"י. Rashi And then he says ותימא, Vetima,
שלמי חגיגה וראיה זמן קבוע להו, shalmei chagigah ure'iyah zman kvi'a lehu,
דעבר הרגל ולא חג אינו חייב באחריותו. da'avar haregel velo chag eino
chayav beachrayuta. You don't bring an עולת ראיה olat re'iyah, or שלמי
חגיגה after the רגל. regel? So הוי דיו בעברת בל תאחר. havei
dei b'averet bal te'acher. ואם
כן, Ve'im ken, יעוותו יעוותו, ya'atvu ya'atvu, like the גמרא says by
פסח. If you brought it at the right time, good, if not,
you blew it. But there's no בל תאחר. bal tascher, יש לומר
דמכל מקום היכא דהופרשו ולא הקריבום קאי עליה בבל תאחר כיון שלא
נפסלו בכך. Yesh lomar d'mikol makom heicha de'ufrishu velo hikrivam ka'ai alai
b'bal te'acher kivan shelo nispaslu b'kach. He says
if you didn't actually sanctify your עולת ראיה and you blew it,
you weren't up for פסח, then you no longer have an obligation.
But if you sanctified the animal and you didn't bring it, then
the animal has a קדושה kedusha of a קרבן, korban, and even
though there's no longer a חיוב chiyuv of bringing an עולת ראיה,
there's a קרבן korban? that is sanctified as an עולה Olah that
has to be brought. Okay, and
so that's תוספות's Tosafot's answer but, again, that's interesting, the idea of
בל תאחר Bal tascher by עולת ראיה, but תוספות Tosafot says not
about your obligation, but about having sanctified the animal. Okay, so now
the גמרא says like this. Rabbi, yes?
Is this- this entire like מדרש הלכה midrash halacha that's parsing the
פסוק pasuk here, like is that all part of the ברייתא תנו
רבנן? braita tnu rabbanan?
Yeah, until it get- yeah, we're still up on the תנו רבנן.
tnu rabbanan. Oh, it's all one מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, this is
all the ברייתא, braita. the parsing of the פסוק.
pasuk Yeah, yeah. We'll see, you'll see when it ends, but so
far we're still in the ברייתא. braita.
Okay, so that's- so that's דרוש ידרשנו, darosh yidrashenu, an obligation that
is
fundamentally not about your- But again, at least it's in the world
of קרבנות. We're still in קרבן korban, and הקדש. hekdesh. We're still
in, you know, territory that's familiar, at least, you know, understandable about
being about בל תאחר. bal tascher, Now the גמרא continues, or the
ברייתא Baraita, continues. ה' אלקיך, Hashem Elokecha, כי דרוש ידרשנו ה' אלקיך,
ki dros yidrashenu Hashem Elokecha, God will seek it out from you.
אלו צדקות ומעשרות ובכור, elu tzedakot umasrot ubachor, צדקה, tzedaka,
מעשר, ma'aser, and בכור. bechor Why is that? Because so רש''י quotes
the פסוק pasuk because it says by צדקות tzedakot? ומעשרות, umasrot it
says ולך תהיה צדקה לפני ה' אלקיך, v'lecha tiye tzedaka lifnei Hashem
Elokecha, and by the מעשר ma'aser it says ואכלת לפני ה' אלקיך
מעשר דגנך תירשך ויצהרך. v'achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha ma'asar degancha tiroshcha v'yitzharecha.
So there's פסוקים by מעשר ma'aser and the question whether בכור bechor
is in this גרסא girsa or not. Anyway, with צדקה tzedaka and
מעשר ma'aser that says ה' אלקיך. Hashem Elokecha. Fine, so that's a
מדרש הלכה, midrash halakha, but conceptually where are we going now? Right?
צדקה Tzedaka isn't something given to God. It isn't about הקדש. hekdesh.
מעשר Ma'aser isn't given to God, you know, מעשר ma'aser is given
to the לויים Leviyim
or to the עניים. aniyim. Although it is true by מעשר, ma'aser,
at least by מעשר ראשון, ma'aser rishon, מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, with
the exception of מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, the תורה fundamentally emphasizes that
it's basically given to God. And then the question is, what does
it mean to give it to God? Well, you give it to
the לויים. Leviyim. But the ברייתא Baraita is a, I mean the
פסוקים do say, you know, כל מעשר הארץ מזרע הארץ לה' הוא.
kol ma'asar ha'aretz mizera ha'aretz l'Hashem hu. So what does it mean
it's לה'? You know, when אברהם Avraham says, you know, or when
יעקב Yaakov says, you know, עם אלקים עמדי, im Elokim imadi, etc.,
וכל אשר תתן לי עשר אעשרנו לך. v'chol asher titein li aser
asrenu lach. What does עשר אעשרנו לך aser asrenu lach mean? Where
do you give the מעשר? ma'aser? What, do you put it on
the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Do you give it to the עניים? aniyim? Do
you give it to a כהן? kohen? So there are different things
you could do with it, but the fundamental idea is first that
you give it back to God. Okay, so you could understand מעשר,
ma'aser, and מעשר ma'aser is verbal, right? You verbally sanctify the thing
and there's an element of, you know, so there's that element that's
similar to a נדר. neder צדקה Tzedaka is not in the context
of being given to God. Again though, you could at least say
צדקה tzedaka still has to do with this verbal aspect. You know,
you obligate yourself, you make a נדר neder to give צדקה, tzedaka,
or if you designate money as צדקה tzedaka money, it has a
type of a קדושה kedusha or a type of a status, which
is learned out from the world of
תרומות trumot ומעשרות ונדרים, unedarim, etc. So therefore, you know, we're leaving
הקדש, hekdesh, but at least the thing that we're still in is
like a נדר, things that have a status based on your speech,
okay? And that through your speech act actually becomes sanctified, okay? It's
called הפלאה hafla'ah in הלכה, which is a speech act that changes
the status. So now we've included צדקה tzedaka and מעשר. ma'aser. Okay.
מעמך, Me'imach, from you, זה לקט שכחה פאה. ze leket shikcha pe'ah.
And this has got to be the strangest inclusion in this, okay?
So and רש''י says it's based on the word עמך, imach, it
says את העני עמך. et he-ani imach. So the idea where the
תורה says עמך imach with you, those poor, those that you have
to take care of because they're your brethren and you have that
responsibility to them, that's the emphasis of the word מעמך, me'imach, there
we're learning to say that that's included in בל תאחר. bal tascher
So this is bizarre for two reasons. It's not about הקדש, hekdesh,
it's not about הפלאה, hafla'ah, okay? And therefore what puts it exactly
in this category is not at all, like, clear.
You know, even as I said, something like מעשר עני, ma'aser ani,
you could say it starts with the idea that it's a tithe
that goes to God, but God then tells me to distribute it
to the עניים. aniyim. לקט ושכחה פאה Leket v'shikcha pe'ah does not
have that basic conceptual structure. It starts not with your responsibility to
God, it starts with your responsibility to עמך, imach, to those that
are with you and part of your society, part of your community.
And therefore again, you know, what else are we going to put
under בל תאחר? bal te'acher. That certainly is the is the strangest.
תוספות Tosafot makes the point that it's even stranger because how could
you be עובר over in בל תאחר? bal te'acher, What's לקט שכחה
פאה? leket shikcha pe'ah? It's I dropped some stuff in my act
of collecting, you know while I was while I was reaping or
I left behind a שכחה, shikcha, a sheaf. So when am I,
how am I עובר over בל תאחר, bal te'acher? right? What does
it mean? I left it behind. בל תאחר bal te'acher means I
waited three חגים. chagim What did I wait three חגים chagim to
do? I waited three חגים chagim to harvest my field? I'm not
עובר over? בל תאחר, bal te'acher right? I can harvest my field
whenever I want to. So what's the scenario that I'm עובר? over
So תוספות Tosafot has two possibilities. One is yes, you violated your
obligation of לקט שכחה פאה leket shikcha pe'ah and you went back
and you took the שכחה, shikcha, and you didn't leave the פאה
pe'ah and you picked up the לקט. leket. And even though now
you've violated the מצוה לקט שכחה פאה, leket shikcha pe'ah, you can
go and make it good, not sort of whatever, you still transgressed,
but you now have to take the stuff that you picked up
and redistribute it to the עניים. aniyim. So the בל תאחר bal
te'acher would be if for your non-redistribution of it to the עניים.
aniyim. That's sort of, you know, how תוספות Tosafot wants it, תוספות,
Tosafot, he imagines. The other is without transgression. He says let's say
there are no עניים aniyim around. I live in this, you know,
all that's around is this farmland for hundreds of miles, no עניים
aniyim are travel around here. What am I supposed to do with
all the לקט שכחה פאה? leket shikcha pe'ah? And if I leave
it and wait for the עניים aniyim to show up it's all
going to rot. So what I'll do is I'll take it all
indoors and I'll hold on to it for the sake of the
עניים. aniyim. And that in that scenario I'm holding onto it for
the sake of the עניים aniyim and I actually did what I'm
supposed to, right? In that case, I have to distribute it within
three רגלים regalim and if I don't I am עובר over on
בל תאחר. bal te'acher So the תוספות Tosafot is previous, like I
said, לקט שכחה ופאה leket shikcha u-peah דף ד'
עמוד ב'
daf
daled amud bet where the גמרא when it first was brought
in the גמרא. Okay. So anyway so
so besides that it doesn't really fit logically into the category, תוספות
Tosafot even raises the practical question of what does it mean not
to pay it to the עניים? aniyim? You're supposed to have left
it initially and he gives two scenarios, one בעבירה be-aveirah and one
sort of doing a, you know, what I'm supposed to do where
I've actually gathered it in and now I have to go back
and distribute it. Now let's also point out about a number of
these besides the trying to find the common denominator, the other bizarre
thing about connecting it to the רגל regel, is what's the logic
of the רגל? regel? Right? I mean the גמרא quoted a פסוק
pasuk which is, you know, חג המצות וחג השבועות, chag ha-matzot ve-chag
ha-shavuot, the פסוק pasuk had nothing to do with בל תאחר, bal
te'acher right? It just has to do oh we have extra words
here since you have to repeat all the חגים et cetera but
why did it think that it's related to בל תאחר? bal te'acher?
Because the obvious logic is if you're talking in the world of
קרבנות or even in the world of הקדש hekdesh שבעולם, she-ba-olam, when
is the most obvious time to satisfy that? When you're anyway going
to ירושלים. Right? That's when you have your opportunity which is why
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says since you have your first opportunity at
the first רגל, regel that's when you're עובר over on בל תאחר
bal te'acher. because if you blew your first opportunity so it's about
having had the opportunity and not making good on it. Okay. Does
that really apply to לקט שכחה ופאה? leket shikcha u-peah? Right? Since
when is that tied into being in ירושלים on the רגל? regel
Or how about like מעשרות ma'asrot or how about צדקות? tzedakot Now
maybe the answer could be yes it does because that's where all
of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael is gathered so if there's ever a
good opportunity to, you know, make good on your obligations not just
to God but to others so when all of the people are
gathered that's a great opportunity to distribute the funds to the poor
and to distribute your obligations to the poor. But again it's interesting
to think how we've shifted and this is now not just about
נדר and not just about הקדש hekdesh but it's about your responsibility
לקט שכחה ופאה, leket shikcha u-peah, מעשרות, ma'asrot, צדקות et cetera and
a not only including them in the בל תאחר bal te'acher category
fundamentally but linking it significantly to the רגל regel. also makes us
focus on another dimension of the significance of the רגל regel in
terms of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Okay. So that's what we have
from that ברייתא. Baraita: And now one more line. והיה
בך חטא, ve-hayah becha chet, there'll be with you a sin, ולא
בקרבנך חטא, ve-lo be-korban'cha chet, your קרבן korban; won't have the sin.
If you were transgressed בל תאחר bal teachair, the קרבן korban is
still valid. You've transgressed but the קרבן korban can still be brought.
Okay. Now we're going to unpack the ברייתא. braita אמר מר, amar
mar, לא תאחר לשלמו, lo te'acher leshalmo, הוא ולא חילופיו. hu ve-lo
chilufav. So we're going to go to the things that the גמרא
thinks are interesting, we're not going to look at every phrase. Okay.
לשלמו, it's only about it, it's not about its substitute. You don't
transgress בל תאחר bal teachair. with its
substitute. חילופי מאי, chilufei mai, what type of substitute or substitute of
what? אי חילופי עולה ושלמים, ei chilufei olah ve-shlamim, if it's a
substitute of an עולה olah or שלמים, מיקרב קרבי. mikrav karvi. What
could a substitute be? It could be תמורה tmurah although then the
גמרא would say תמורה tmurah which is you sort of say זה
תחת זה zeh tachat zeh and then it doesn't work but the
other thing becomes קדוש. kadosh. חילופיו chilufav would be a more התר
heter scenario which is you miss you lost your עולה olah and
שלמים so you sanctified another animal and brought it instead and then
you found the one that you lost. Okay so then it's so
that's now been substituted for. Okay so let's take a
look.
Oh so actually in that case let's say but then it wouldn't
be the substitute it'd be the one substituted for. You separated off
A. You were מקדיש makdish A. It got lost. Okay. Here you
were מקדיש makdish A as your עולה, olah, it got lost, so
then you were מקדיש makdish B as your עולה, olah, then you
found A.
Did you bring B already?
No you didn't bring then you found A and you decided to
bring it. So in that case B it was the substitute for
A but it was never brought but it was sanctified.
So you're not עובר over on בל תאחר bal teachair on B.
Well the גמרא is going to reject that it's going to say
you are but that would be the most obvious scenario of חילופיו.
chilufav. Okay. So then it does so it says if that's the
case so it says אי חילופי עולה ושלמים מיקרב קרבי, ei chilufei
olah ve-shlamim mikrav karvi,
so they can be brought and if it can be brought why
shouldn't you be עובר over on בל תאחר? bal teachair You sanctified
it. אי חילופי חטאת, ei chilufei chatat, if it was a scenario
like that but it was a חטאת, chatat, you lost the חטאת,
chatat you sanctified another one, you found the original. So what do
you do with a חטאת that you are נתכפרו באחר? למיתה אזלא.
le-mitah azla.
You have to let it die. It doesn't get brought as a
קרבן. korban Okay so that's בל תאחר. bal teachair So I mean
how could there be בל תאחר bal teachair. about that? אלא מאי
חילופיו, ella mai chilufav, so what would be an example of חילופיו?
chilufav? חילופי תודה. chilufei todah.
It's a case like this if the animal's lost and you sanctified
another one but with not the קרבן korban we're talking about is
a תודה. todah. Now why is that significant? Because דתני רב חייה,
de-tani Rav Chiya, תודה שנתערבה בתמורתה, todah she-nit'arevah bi-tmuratah,
so a תודה todah which was mixed up with its תמורה. tmurah.
it's its תמורה *tmurah*. Again, תמורה *tmurah* would be a violation way
of getting a חליפה *chalifah* that you said הרי זו harei zo
תחת זו *harei zu tachat zu*, but חילופיו *chilufav* is a legitimate
way because the first one was lost. But anyway, you have now
a תודה *Todah* and its and its substitute. And they got mixed
up. Now, what's the significance? The significance is that a תודה *Todah*
a תודה *Todah* is only
comes with the bread. You know it comes with the 40 loaves
of bread. חילופי תודה *chilufei Todah* does not come with the loaves
of bread. You would bring it as a sacrifice but it doesn't
come with the loaves of bread. So here, you basically had your
first thing and you sanctified it as a תודה *Todah*, then it
got lost, you made another thing as a תודה *Todah*, then you
found the original one. Okay? Or you could just say that you
did a תמורה *tmurah*, you said זו תחת זו *zu tachat zu*.
So this is a תמורת תודה *tmurat Todah* or a חליפי תודה
*chalifei Todah*. Now only this one has bread. Okay, the other one
will not. You'll bring it but it won't get bread with it.
Now, that's if you know which is which. Let's say they get
mixed up. So now you don't know, right, which one is A
and which one is B. Okay, you just have two and you
don't know, one of them is A and one of them is
B, you don't know which is which. Comes with חמץ *chametz*, right?
What? Now חמץ *chametz*, exactly.
Well, 10 loaves are חמץ *chametz*. Okay, so so which is which?
So in this case if you had both of them around, you
bring both of them, you bring your 40 loaves of bread, okay,
and you basically say, whichever one of them is the תודה *Todah*,
these loaves go with that. Okay, you don't have to know which
is which, you just bring both of them, and the loaves are
connected to whichever one is the תודה *Todah*. But let's say not
only you not know which is which, but one of them is
no longer around, one of them died. Now you're stuck. Do I
bring this do I bring this or not? If I bring it
if it's not the תודה *Todah*, then I can't bring it with
the bread. If it is the תודה *Todah*, then I can't bring
it without the bread. Like couldn't you just say that?
Like you say a conditional statement.
What would the conditional statement be? If this oh, if this is
a תודה *Todah* then this bread... because well what's the sort of
what's the alternative? Well no, but what's also the significance of the
bread?
Wouldn't it be just a gift? And the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* eat
the bread anyway, right? חולין בעזרה *chullin b'azarah*. It's not the
bread's not burned up, they eat it, right?
Yeah, but
so the question is why not you know what would you what
would be the bad of just saying here's the bread
and it would be sanctified it's sanctified
if it's not...
What do you do with the bread?
It's a good question. Yeah,
I've
been... I'm just thinking. One minute.
Yeah, I'm not sure. It's a good question why you can't sort
of bring it בתנאי *b'tnai*. I'll have to get back to you
on that. But okay, but the assumption is that if you don't
know, you can't be sure that the bread is going to be
relevant and connected, you don't bring it. So let's take a look.
דתניא detanya *detanya*... okay where were we? דתניא רבי חייא *detanya Rebbe
Chiya*: תודה שנתערבה בתמורתה *Todah she'nit'arva bitmuratah* ומתה אחת מהן *umeta achat
mehen*, חברתה אין לה תקנה *chavertah ein lah takkanah*. So you don't
have you can't have anything to do with the one that's left.
היכי יעביד *heichi ya'avid*, what should you do? ליקרביה וליקרביה לחם בהדה
*likreivei v'likreivei lechem bahadah*, bring it with the bread? דילמא תמורה היא
*dilma tmurah hi*. I mean I think Charlie is right that the
biggest issue would be that since the bread is part of the
act of הקרבה *hakravah*, it would be a חולין בעזרה *chullin b'azarah*
problem and it's not just a סתם תנאי *stam tnai*. But ליקרביה
בלא לחם *likreivei belo lechem*, bring it without the bread? דילמא תודה
היא *dilma Todah hi*. Okay, so therefore that's the case that's a
חליפי תודה *chalifei Todah* which you can't bring and you're not over
בל תאחר bal t'acher. *Bal Ta'acher*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one
minute: דהא כיון דלאו בר הקרבה היא *deha keivan d'lav bar hakravah
hi*, קרא למעוטי למה לי *k'ra l'mautei lamah li*? If you can't
bring it, why do you have to tell me you're not over
בל תאחר bal t'acher *Bal Ta'acher*? It's like the חטאת שמתה *Chatat
shemetah*, of course you're not over בל תאחר bal t'acher *Bal Ta'acher*,
there's no way to bring it. So either you do bring it
and you're over בל תאחר bal t'acher *Bal Ta'acher*, or you don't
bring it and you're not allowed to bring it and then therefore
there's no, of course you're not over בל תאחר bal t'acher. *Bal
Ta'acher*. What is the case that a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* had to
tell me you're not over on בל תאחר bal t'acher *Bal Ta'acher*?
Either you are or it's obvious. Okay? So the גמרא *Gemara* says:
אמר רב ששת *Amar Rav Sheshes*, לעולם למעוטי חילופי עולה olah ושלמים
*le'olam l'mautei chilufei olah v'shelamim*. Go back to your simple case of
something that was sanctified instead of an עולה ושלמים *olah v'shelamim* and
then you found the original. Okay, so you are over on בל
תאחר *Bal Ta'acher*, this is a קרבן korban *korban*, what's the issue?
והכא במאי עסקינן כגון שעברו עליו שני רגלים regalim *v'hacha bemai askinan
k'gon she'avru alav shenei regalim*. So here's the case of חילופי *chilufei*,
not that it was lost. Here's what it means exchanged. You sanctified
an עולה *olah*. It's been two רגלים *regalim*. It's been פסח ושבועות
*Pesach v'Shavuos*.
And then it got a מום mum *mum*. And then you need
to bring this by סוכות Sukkot *Succos*. Okay, now this animal got
a מום mum. *mum*. וחיללו על אחר *v'chillalo al acher*. So what
do you do? In that case what has a מום mum *mum*,
you transfer the קדושה kedusha *kedusha*. Okay, so you transfer the קדושה
kedusha *kedusha*, I mean first you know you do a תמורה *tmurah*
and from money to the other animal, but you transfer the קדושה
kedusha *kedusha* to another קרבן korban *korban*.
That's וחיללו *v'chillalo*.
Right. דעבר עליו *de-avar alav*. רגל regel אחד and now this second
קרבן, korban it now became סוכות. Sukkot. So what's the story? Have
you transgressed בל תאחר, right? Because this animal you got the scenario,
right?
Here's your—it's not the original animal, right? Here's your פסח, שבועות, and
סוכות.
Sukkot. Okay, so here's your cow, right? And it's now been, I
don't know what that way—anyway, it's now been one,
two, if it gets to be סוכות Sukkot. and you don't bring
it, it's בל תאחר. But somewhere here it got a מום mum?
and you substituted it for a different cow. You sanctified, you know,
you transferred it
to—it's a Red Heifer! There you go. And now this cow crosses
the finish line into סוכות. Sukkot Are you עובר over on בל
תאחר or not? Is it the same קדושה kedusha seen as the
same קרבן? korban Or because it's a new animal you start counting
the three רגלים?
Great question, but why would you be עובר over on בל תאחר
anyway? You've made it within the three... No, you
don't, because you don't bring it on סוכות. Sukkot.
Right, if you don't, assuming you're not, assuming you don't bring it
on סוכות. Sukkot?
Ah, but you could be, you could make חילופי חילופין לעדי עדי
עולם. chilufei chilufin le'adei adei olam. Keep on getting a מום. Okay,
so it says like this.
It says והכא במאי עסקינן כגון שעברו עליו שני
רגלים והומם וחיללו
על אחר ועבר עליו רגל אחד,
ve'hacha be'mai askinan kegon she'avru alav shnei regalim ve'humam
ve'chilalo
al acher ve'avar alav regel echad, right? And that last one, the
new קרבן, korban now went through the third רגל. regel סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Sal ka'daitach amina I would have thought הואיל ומכח קמא קאתי
כמאן דעברו עליו ג' רגלים דמי, ho'il u'mikach kama ka'ati keman de'avru
alav gimel regalim dami, since it's a transfer of קדושה from the
first one, it's like three רגלים. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan,
that it's not that way, that this animal itself you have not
been עובר over on. By the way, if the person said
הרי עלי עולה, harei alai olah,
then presumably he would be עובר over. because then the question is
have you satisfied the vow you made on yourself? But if he
said הרי זו עולה, harei zo olah, then the point is that
this animal has not been brought for three רגלים, then it focuses
on the animal.
That's the difference between נדר and נדבה. nedavah. Yeah, exactly.
Okay, so the גמרא says like this, ולרבי מאיר—so u'le'Rabbi Meir that's
a great read of the ברייתא, braita but that assumes you need
three רגלים or at least two so you have the scenario. ולרבי
מאיר דאמר כיון שעבר עליו רגל אחד עובר בבל תאחר מאי איכא
למימר? u'le'Rabbi Meir de'amar keivan she'avar alav regel echad over be'bal teachair
mai ika le'meimar?
Where's your scenario? If it hasn't been the רגל regel? yet, then
you've—and you transfer the קדושה—so it's just one רגל regel? like any
other thing. If the רגל regel? has passed, you've already been עובר.
over What's the scenario where exchanging it in the middle might make
a difference? So the גמרא says אמר רבא הכא במאי עסקינן כגון
שהומם בתוך הרגל וחיללו ועבר עליו הרגל. amar Rava hacha be'mai askinan
kegon she'humam betoch ha'regel ve'chilalo ve'avar alav ha'regel. Okay,
it was in the middle of סוכות
according to Rabbi Meir, or let's
say, I don't know, פסח. Here was day one of פסח and
here's day seven of פסח and it got a מום on day
three and you transferred it. So this one you weren't עובר over
on בל תאחר because it didn't go till the end of פסח.
This one only got the קדושה in the middle. Here's a חידוש
chiddush according to Rabbi Meir, right? What does it mean one רגל?
regel. Does it mean it has to pass through the whole רגל?
regel Let's say somebody sanctifies or says הרי זו in the middle
of סוכות. Are they עובר over on the last day of סוכות?
Or does it have to go through the whole רגל? regel. So
this גמרא is assuming it has to go through the whole רגל.
regel. So this one didn't go through the whole רגל regel and
that one didn't go through the whole רגל. regel But if you
see it as a continuation, then you are עובר over on בל
תאחר.
So it's the same, it's the exact same scenario except not in
between רגלים but in the middle of a רגל.
Okay. סלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל ומכח קמא קאתי כמאן דעבר עליו כולו
רגל דמי, salka da'atach amina ho'il u'mikach kama ka'ati keman de'avar alav
kulo regel dami, I would have thought
since it's coming from the first one it's like the entire רגל
passed over. קא משמע לן, k'mashma lan no, that you start the
clock again,
okay?
So that's the case of חילופין chilufin that you don't restart the
clock, you start the clock again. Okay, now. והיה בך חטא ולא
בקרבנך חטא, ve'haya becha cheit velo be'korbanacha cheit, going now towards the
end of the ברייתא again. The things that are on the list
don't interest the גמרא—they totally interest me about what type of list
it is—but the גמרא is focusing more on like some of the
exceptions. The sin will be in you and not in your קרבן;
korban your קרבן korban. remains כשר. kasher. So the גמרא says דהא
מהכא נפקא? de'ha mehacha nafka? Is that where we learn it from?
מידכם נפקא. miyadechem nafka. We learn it from another source. דתניא, we
taught a ברייתא: אחרים, Acherim, others,
meaning Rabbi Meir, says: יכול יהא בכור
שעבר עליו שנתו כפסולי המוקדשין ויפסל? yachol yehei bechor she'avar alav shnato
kefsulei hamukdashin ve'yipaseil?
Maybe if a בכור bechor. is not brought in the first year,
right, when it's supposed to be brought, so maybe it becomes invalid,
it's like, you know, it's like an animal with a מום? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says "ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך מעשר דגנך
תירושך ויצהרך ובכורות בקרך וצאנך". ve'achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha ma'asar degancha tiroshcha
ve'yitzharecha u'vechorot bekarcha ve'tzonacha.
You eat your מעשר ma'aser and your בכור. bechor מקיש בכור למעשר.
makish bechor le'ma'aser.
It links the בכור bechor to the מעשר. ma'aser. מה מעשר אינו
נפסל משנה לחברתה, ma ma'aser eino nipsel mishana lachaverta, the same way
מעשר ma'aser you can give in a later year, because the whole
idea, you know, is after three years if you haven't given up
your מעשרות, ma'asrot, then you clean out your house every three years.
So מעשר ma'aser clearly can be given a year,
more than a year late,
אף בכור... af bechor... So therefore you can implicitly see that the
קרבן korban is not נפסל nifsal just cause you were עובר over
on בל תאחר.
בכור bechor can be given it seems from this even five years
later.
Yeah. So the Gemara says אף so don't you learn it from
this פסוק that the קרבן isn't נפסל? nifsal? It says אצטריך itztrich
no you needed the other פסוק as well. סלקא דעתך אמינא I
would have said הני מילי בכור דלאו בר הרצאה הוא. hani mili
bechor d'lav bar hartza'ah hu. That's by a בכור bechor which the
בכור bechor is not coming for יעשה ye'aseh or רצוי ritzuy to
find favor in God's eyes fundamentally it is you know it's given
as a gift Rashi says. אבל קדשים דבני הרצאה נינהו Aval kodshim
d'vnei hartza'ah ninhu קדשים kodshim where there's an idea of לרצון l'ratzon
and they're coming for הרצאה hartza'ah to sort of to give to
there's a better word than it I was going to say curry
favor with God but anyway אימא לא לירצו eima lo liyirtzu maybe
it should not be accepted for a רצוי ritzuy purpose קא משמע
לן that it is. Now that idea of רצוי ritzuy is interesting
right? Because like you know by a for example
you have an idea of the קרבן being כשר kosher and not
being עולה לבעלים לשם חובה. oleh l'ba'alim l'shem chovah. We had that
in the beginning of זבחים Zevachim a lot. If you שחט shacht
a קרבן שלא לשמה shelo l'shmah the קרבן is כשר kosher could
be eaten but the בעלים ba'alim have not fulfilled their obligation. Okay
so that could be like one sense but by a בכור bechor.
you know as long as the קרבן was כשר kosher and the
כהנים eat it it's like there's no sense of like an אכיל
achil other than that. But the Gemara doesn't even frame it that
way of not being יוצא your obligation. It frames it more as
this idea of הרצאה hartza'ah like which means that you know and
that gets to the question about like what's the function of a
בכור. bechor Most of the קרבנות are fundamentally brought to to God
right? Whether it's a for sin or an עולה or a שלמים
it's basically a way of you connecting to God like we would
sort of say תפילה tefillah connecting in different ways but you give
something to God as a way of connecting to God and there's
that idea of that it's
לרצון l'ratzon right and לרצון l'ratzon is a common word the Torah
uses by קרבנות particularly in the context of שלמים. By בכור bechor
it sounds like it's a little bit different. It sounds like בכור
bechor the very act and you could say the same is true
about מעשר. ma'aser. The very act of sanctifying it is fundamentally what
you're supposed to do. You have a firstborn that's God's. If you
have a tithe that's God's and it's not that the act of
bringing it is supposed to somehow be an act of connecting you
to God. It's sort of like we talked before about the מעשר
ma'aser you separate the מעשר ma'aser that's God's. What do you do
with it? Alright I'll give it to the לוי. Levi. Okay I'll
give it to the עניים. aniyim. Okay I'll do this with it.
But the fundamental religious act is the separating of the tithe to
God and the separating of the בכור bechor to God and not
that the bringing of it is about some type of a through
bringing the sacrifice I'm going to connect to God. And that seems
to be the point the Gemara's making about this difference of רצון.
ratzon. So maybe the בל תאחר would get in the way of
saying that this is a meaningful religious connection since it's being done
since you sinned in the process of this Rashi even says the
idea of מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah. So and so that's
one thing to say by בכור bechor it's okay that's not about
connecting to God right? The very giving of the בכור bechor and
sanctifying of it that was the primary thing. Other קרבנות which are
basically like a type of a תפילה if you want to use
our sort of a more post post קרבן concept you know that
maybe is sullied by the by the sense of the of the
בל תאחר and that's why the פסוק says no the קרבן is
completely okay you have whatever עבירה aveirah you have this קרבן is
completely okay even in terms of this רצוי ritzuy element. Charlie what
did you want to add?
Two things oh this
פסח would seem to be different here.
Yeah so פסח also you could say is not לרצון l'ratzon is
not רצוי. ritzuy. Of course פסח you don't need בל תאחר for
right. Second it's מעשר ma'aser also מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah is interesting
about that as well whether you have that concept by מעשר בהמה
ma'aser behemah but yeah and
if this is really thinking Rabbi Meir
you'd be עובר over after one רגל not just a year and
this would be should be a slightly different that's true
but but again so but it's
but as long as you buy into this דרשה drasha right it's
relevant for as long as you use all the different approaches. Anyway
the Gemara makes the point that not only בכור all קרבנות you're
still יוצא whether you know even in the רצוי ritzuy aspect of
them even if you're עובר בל תאחר. We'll just read one more
line. The Gemara
says ואכתי ve'achati the Gemara says מדי בן עזאי נפקא midei Ben
Azzai nafka we can learn it from בן עזאי. Ben Azzai. דתניא
we taught in a ברייתא בן עזאי אומר אותו Ben Azzai omer
oto it says by פיגול pigul it says המקריב אתו לא יחשב
לו פגול יהיה hamakriv oto lo yeichashev lo pigul yiheyeh right if
you have the wrong thought you invalidate the
קרבן. מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud lomar? לפי שנאמר לא תאחר לשלמו
lefi shenemar lo te'acher l'shalmo says the ברייתא בן עזאי Ben Azzai
שומע אני אף מאחר נדרו בבל ירצה shomei'a ani af me'acher nidro
b'val yeiratzeh again the issue of רצוי. ritzuy. Maybe if you violated
בל תאחר the קרבן is not
accepted? So תלמוד לומר talmud lomar אותו oto no only by
פיגול. pigul. אותו לא ירצה ואין מאחר נדרו בלא ירצה. oto lo
yeratzeh v'ein me'acher nidro b'lo yeratzeh. פיגול *Pigul* is not desired by
God. Another קרבן *Korban*, even one that you were עובר *over* on
בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*, is desired by God. Not only is it
a good כשר *kosher* קרבן *Korban*, but it even has this element
of רצוי *Ritzuy*, whatever חטא *cheit* you did in delaying its bringing.
So we will find out tomorrow what the idea is about, about,
you know, that ולא בקרבנך חטא *v'lo b'korban'cha cheit*, since we are
now claiming that we already know that concept from other sources, what
is that point of saying ולא בקרבנך חטא *v'lo b'korban'cha cheit*?